<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The boasting Baptist dismounted, and the Beast disarmed and sorely wounded without any carnal weapon. In a reply to some papers, written by Jonathan Iohnson, of Lincolne, as an answer to a letter, sent him by Martin Mason, concerning some exceptions against several truths.  / Published by a faithfull minister, not of the letter, but of the everlasting Gospel.</title>
            <author>Mason, Martin, fl. 1650-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89634</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M924</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E877_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202884</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863023</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863023</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115205</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89634)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115205)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 132:E877[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The boasting Baptist dismounted, and the Beast disarmed and sorely wounded without any carnal weapon. In a reply to some papers, written by Jonathan Iohnson, of Lincolne, as an answer to a letter, sent him by Martin Mason, concerning some exceptions against several truths.  / Published by a faithfull minister, not of the letter, but of the everlasting Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Mason, Martin, fl. 1650-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at the Black-spread-Eagle neer the west-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Martin Mason.</note>
                  <note>A reply to an untraced work by Jonathan Johnson.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill: 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Johnson, Jonathan, --  of Lincoln --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Controversial literature --  Quaker authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115205:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Boaſting Baptiſt DISMOVNTED, AND THE BEAST Diſarmed and ſorely wounded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Carnal Weapon.</p>
            <p>IN A REPLY TO Some <hi>Papers,</hi> Written by <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than Iohnſon,</hi> of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> as an Anſwer to a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſent him by <hi>Martin Maſon,</hi> concerning ſome exceptions againſt ſeveral Truths.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by a Faithfull Miniſter, not of the Letter, but of the Everlaſting Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>After the manner of men have I fought with Beaſts,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 15.32.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>The mighty men of Babylon, their might hath failed, they became as women; her Bars are broken: The Daughter of Babylon is like a Threſhing-Floore, it is time to threſh her,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 51.30.33.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>You onely have I known of all the Families of the earth, therefore will I puniſh you for all your iniquities,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Amos 3.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Black-ſpread-Eagle neer the weſt-end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:115205:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115205:2"/>
            <head>The Boaſting Baptiſt diſmounted: &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Jonathan Johnſon,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HOU art groſsly miſtaken to think thy ſelf garriſon'd in <hi>Sion,</hi> while thou art thus mewed up in the beaſtly pinfold of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and haſt no better Bul-works then her muddy Walls, her tottering Towers to defend thee, the meer I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations of thy own brain, humane Inventions, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy falacies, Antichriſtian Conſequences, conjured up out of the bottomleſs pit.</p>
            <p>Though thou boaſteſt in thy babbling, and diſdainfully tells me of the weakneſs and diſarmed condition of me, and thoſe I am encamped with,<note place="margin">Mark. 5.9.</note> and that <hi>our weapon is but a Bulruſh;</hi> yet 'tis not thee, nor thy <hi>Fathers Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> can make one Souldier in the Camp of the Lord, give one inch of ground to the lyar, or turn his back to the uncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtine; and though the weapons of our warfare be not carnall yet do the wicked receive ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible wounds,</hi> and ſo doſt thou, which will make thee gnaſh thy teeth in ſecret.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.4.</note> 'Tis the conquering Power of the Sword of the Spirit which is our Weapon, (that's no <hi>Bulruſh,</hi> and that ſhall the Boaſter witneſs when the wrath of the Lord falls upon him) and by that ſhall Antichriſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. Amongſt other things I asked thee,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.17.</note> 
               <hi>hath every one that comes into the world, heard and read the preachings of Chriſt and his Apoſtles as they are tranſcribed in the Bible?</hi> and thou anſwers, <hi>They have all heard.</hi> But muſt the lyar in thee be received for the Oracle of God?<note place="margin">2 Sam. 16.23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>May not Millions of men and women in the world, who dwell in thoſe parts not counted Chriſtendome, witneſs againſt thee? If an <hi>Egyptian</hi> Myſt had not blinded thee, thou couldſt not have been thus beſotted, as to back thy lye with thoſe places of the Letter, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. which in effect prove Chriſts command to his Diſciples, when they were upon earth, to go and preach the glad tydings of the Goſpel to that Generation they lived in:</p>
            <p>The Commiſſion nor the Execution whereof, thou never heard me
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115205:3"/>queſtion; but what's this to the proof of thy anſwer to my queſtion? O ſee thy ſottiſhneſs and be aſhamed! Remember thou art a Debtor to me for an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to thoſe <hi>quaeries; how is the Goſpel preached to every creature under heaven, if it he not by that Principle of Light in the conſcience? Does not that which ſhews ſin and evil in the Conſcience, draw the creature out of ſin if the creature be guided by it? And does not that which draws out of ſin, lead to chriſt the Saviour? and is not that the firſt Principle?</hi> Were not theſe things worth thy taking notice of? Or, did not that of God in thee convince thee of the truth herein, but the man of ſin in thee would not ſuffer thee to own the Truth: Yet when thou writes again, give a plain anſwer to each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, in the mean time, take back this Brat of thy own begetting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Principle of light ariſing in the conſcience; is from that preaching of Repentance and Faith by the Apoſtle.</hi> So that take away the Letter, and by this mans Doctrine there would be no Principle of Light ariſing in the conſcience; Oh the groſs darkneſs of this <hi>Babylonian!</hi> Shame cover the face of the lyar; Was there not a Principle of Light in the people, who lived before <hi>Moſes</hi> writ the Letter? VVas not <hi>Moſes</hi> upon earth before the <hi>preaching of Repentance and Faith by the Apoſtles?</hi> Nay, doſt thou not ſay in the ſame Paper, <hi>That that ſound of accuſing or excuſing is in all conſciences?</hi> If it be in all conſciences, (as indeed it is) then it muſt needs be in the conſciences of millions of people, who never heard the preaching of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and Faith by the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> Now to thy ſcornfull queſtion, <hi>VVhere have I, or any of thoſe who run abroad, come, but they have heard the preachings of chriſt before our coming?</hi> To this I anſwer, <hi>The wrath of the Lord, not his Bleſſing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 1. Gen. 1.2. 1 Tim. 3.16. Col. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>is to thee, who ſitteſt in the ſeat of the ſcornfull. Now for the people, they have all heard the ſound of Chriſts voice, preaching in their conſciences, but darkneſs being upon the face of the earth, they knew not the Myſtery of godlineſs, Chriſt in them the hope of glory: If thou wouldſt own the letter, as thou preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, thou durſt not deny chriſt to be in all, Iew and Greek, Barbarian, Scithi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, bond and free.</hi> I own no other Goſpel but what the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> preached, nor do we direct the people to any other thing then the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> did, <hi>that ſure word of Propheſie</hi> (the Light in their conſciences) <hi>unto which they do well if they take heed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.39. 1 John 1. Rom 1.16.</note> we only ſend them to the Seed of the woman, which is the word of God, the Unction, or Chriſt within, who is the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God unto ſalvation. But the Letter is not the ſure word of Propheſie, the Seed of the Woman, the Unction, or Chriſt within, the Word of God, or Goſpel, which is the Power of God unto Salvation. <hi>I</hi> do appeal to that of God in every mans conſcience, if the Seed of the Serpent, the man of ſin, be not within; muſt not then the Seed of the Woman be there alſo?<note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> how ſhall the Seed of the Woman break the Sepents head, if the Seed of the Woman be not where the Serpent is? For this Royall Seed of God diſcovers the Tempter to the creature in his firſt motion, if the creature minde to be guided by this good Seed;<note place="margin">Prov. 1.10.</note> and as he beleeves in this Son of Gods love, who reveals the man of ſin, the Thief is ſeen, but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115205:3"/>not conſented to, the Devill being reſiſted flies away;<note place="margin">1 John 12.</note> ſo as many as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this Royall Seed, this Son of Gods Love, the Light of Chriſt Jeſus ſhining in their conſciences, by beleeving therein, <hi>from him they receive power to become the Sons of God;</hi> for through faith in Chriſt Jeſus, ſhining into the conſcience, all things are poſſible, the heart is thereby purified, and without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God; no pleaſing of God till the heart be purified, and no purifying of the heart but by Faith in the Son of God ſhining into the heart, there convincing the creature of ſin in ſecret, and then <hi>how dare I do this wickedneſs and ſin againſt my God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 21.23. He fills heaven and earth with his preſence. Col. 1.26.</note> who is not at a diſtance? he is not a God afar off, but nigh at hand, even in the heart, and ſees the ſecrets of the heart: But this is a Myſtery to all carnall mindes, it was a Myſtery in the dayes of the Apoſtles, hid from Ages and Generations paſt, but was then, and is now made manifeſt to his Saints; the riches of the Glory of this Myſtery among the Gentils, <hi>Chriſt in them the hope of Glory,</hi> hid from the wiſe and prudent of the world, and revealed unto babes. No other Chriſt, no other Word do we preach, but that which the Prophets and Apoſtles did bear witneſs of, <hi>that which we have ſeen with our eyes, and heard with our ears,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 1. Rom. 10.8. Heb. 5.6. John 6.68.</note> 
               <hi>that word which is even in the heart and in the mouth;</hi> to this Everlaſting Prieſt, which hath the Word of eternall life, do we exhort the people to be obedient; and who keep to this Annointing in them, need not that any man teach them, nor ſuch be ſeduced by the Serpent.</p>
            <p>Thou tells me of confeſſing the Apoſtles, ſaying, <hi>This is the VVord of Faith which we preach, and the hearing of that VVord of Faith, the light in the conſcience, is the in-let to the Spirit of Promiſc;</hi> and then thou asks me, if this be not the ſame which thou ſayeſt <hi>&amp;c.</hi> O ſhameleſs man! Doſt thou not in that exception of thine to the firſt Poſition, cry up the Letter, and ſay the hearing and receiving of that is the in-let to the Spirit of Promiſe, and thoſe who do not hear and obey that as the Teachings of God; have not his Spirit? and yet dares thou come thus impudently to bluſter againſt me, and tax me for a falſe accuſer? but ſhame ſhall cover thee, and the hand of the Lord ſhall finde thee out. Yet be it remembred, that here thou haſt owned <hi>the Light in the conſcience to be the in-let to the Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</hi> Thou bids me, if I can prove any jugling by thee, do it. Haſt thou not ſaved me ſome labour and done it thy ſelf? one while owning the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be the in-let to the Spirit of Promiſe, and another time owning the Light in the conſcience to be the Spirit of Promiſe; ſometimes calling the Letter the Rule, and ſometimes the Spirit for the Rule. Doſt thou not ſay thy Foundation is not built upon <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> as they were men, but upon their preaching the Word of God, and Jeſus? Is not thy Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation built upon the Letter? doſt thou not account that for the Word of God which they preached?</p>
            <p>But what's thy meaning to ſay upon their preaching, the Word of God and Jeſus? Is the Word of God and Jeſus two diſtinct things? Is there
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115205:4"/>any other Word of God beſide Jeſus?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13. Rom. 1.16.</note> Is not he called the Word of God? Is not the Word of God beleeved in, the Power of God unto ſalvation? Does thou not beleeve the Letter to be the Word of God? yet neither is it, nor thy belief there, the Power of God to ſave thee from the beaſtly ſins of lying, pride, paſlion, and bitter ſpiritedneſs, and confuſion.</p>
            <p>Thou makes thy ſelf merry with that expreſſion of mine, <hi>That which gave forth the</hi> Leaves <hi>town, it is my witneſs againſt thee, and all thy deceitfull juglings.</hi> Thou Replyes, <hi>The Printer gave forth the</hi> Leaves, <hi>and ſo the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> thou ſayes, <hi>is my witneſs, &amp;c.</hi> And then backs that lye with another Brat of thy own begetting, <hi>that neither Printer, nor any thing printed from the voice of Truth, will witneſs with</hi> me, <hi>or be for</hi> me. But the tongue of the lyar is not to be beleeved.</p>
            <p>Had I dealt with the deceitfulleſt Pariſh-Prieſt in the Nation, could I have found a more filthy gloſs put upon that innocent Expreſſion, (<hi>that which gave forth the</hi> Leaves <hi>I own?</hi>) Could I have met with leſs ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in a <hi>Pagan Prieſt,</hi> then is found in this high-flown <hi>Phariſee?</hi> But friends you may ſee the man is put to his ſhifts, while he is fain to make uſe of this ſhuſhing.</p>
            <p>Was it not the pure Spirit of the living God that gave forth the Letter? That, and no other Spirit do I own, and that is my witneſs againſt the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit, lording it in thee, <hi>Ionathan Iohnſen,</hi> who ſayes the Printer gave forth the Leaves: Shame cover the lyar, does not the Printer ſell them to the Stationers? But know this, <hi>Alying tongue is an Abomination to the Lord, and the Lake is the Portion of the lyar:</hi> Rev. 21.8.</p>
            <p>Poor man, how art thou puzled and tormented, becauſe in my Paper I cry not up the Letter, but owns Chriſt alone, who is the Light in the conſcience, to be the in-let to the Spirit of Promiſe. Why does the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then rage,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.1.</note> and the man imagine ſuch a vain thing, as to think I ſhould own thy Baptiſm with water, which thou painteſt over with the name of the Baptiſm of Repentance, to be the in-let to the Spirit of Promiſe? Theſe are thy words, <hi>That which is the in-let to the Spirit of Promiſe into the heart, is the door and the way; but the Baptiſm of Repentance, the hearing of Faith preached, or beleeving, is the in-let to the Spirit of Promiſe; therefore the Baptiſm of Repentance, and the hearing of Faith preached, and beleeving, is the in-let to the Spirit of Promiſe:</hi> So that none, by this mans Doctrine, can have the Spirit, who bow not to his ſprinckling. Tell me, <hi>Ionathan,</hi> didſt thou not a little before, own the Light in the Conſcience to be the in-let to the Spirit of Promiſe, and call me falſe accuſer for ſaying thou deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edſt it?<note place="margin">Matt. 23.32.</note> Fye <hi>Ionathan,</hi> lye; wilt thou needs be a lyar whether I will or no? thou art haſtning on apace to fill up the meaſure of thy iniquities, and then ſhall the wrath of the Lord ſeize upon thee. Judge, O ye wiſe in heart, if this Babler be not a Bond-ſlave in <hi>Babylon;</hi> does he not ſay and unſay? Does he not here place his Water, and beleeving in the Letter, in the room of Chriſt, by making them the Way, and the Door, or in-let
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115205:4"/>to the Spirit of Promiſe: whoever are not ſpiritually blinde, will ſee the blaſphemy of the Beaſt, for Chriſt the Light of the world, is the Door, and the Way, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.9. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.16. and ſo the in-let to the Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; and where muſt the creature look for Chriſt, if not within: Is not that the Light of Chriſt which tells every man and woman in ſecret of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſin he doth commit, and perſwades the creature not to run on in the evill of his wayes: Does not Chriſt ſtand at the door and knock:<note place="margin">Rev. 3.20.</note> Is not this door the heart of man: Does he not fill Heaven and Earth with his preſence: <hi>Thy Redeemer is in the midſt of thee, O Iſrael.</hi> Tell me, <hi>Ionathan,</hi> was the hearing of faith, which thou brings in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. for proof of thy blaſphemy, the hearing of the Prophets, or of <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles: Or was it not a beleeving in that Chriſt which <hi>Paul</hi> preached to be in all, Jew and Greek, Barbarian, Scithian,<note place="margin">Coll. 3.11.</note> bond and free; in that Chriſt who is the Light in all conſciences, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there to every man and woman upon earth. And what ſhall be the condemnation of all Man-kinde,<note place="margin">Joh. 3.19.</note> who never heard of the Name of Chriſt at Jeruſalem, if not the Light of Jeſus Chriſt placed in the Conſcience: And wherefore is the Light of Jeſus left there in the heart of every man and woman, if not to lead man and women out of ſin unto holineſs: And whether any thing without can redeem a ſoul from ſin, but that Jeſus who is the Light of the world, and ſhines into the conſcience of every man and woman in the world. When thou writes again, anſwer thoſe plain Quaeries, without any Serpentine Evaſions, conjuring Conſequences, or Antichriſtian Falacies.</p>
            <p>As for thy ſecond Proof, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. When thou and thy Friends can witneſs ſuch a condition as theſe Convicts could in the four laſt <hi>Verſes</hi> of that <hi>Chapter,</hi> thou ſayes ſomthing; till then, let the Babler be ſilent and leave his boaſting, for the Baptiſm of Repentance from dead works, he knows not, ſo long as he lives in lying, pride and paſſion: Beſides, Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprinckling is not once named there: <hi>Does Chriſts Baptiſm conſiſt of outward water; Or, is not his a Baptiſm of ſufferings, with the Holy Ghoſt and with Fire: And art thou baptized with this Baptiſm, and ſo much droſs of lying, falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing, pride and paſſion, not burnt up in thee.</hi> Anſwer thoſe three <hi>quaeries</hi> in ſingleneſs of heart, or elſe let the Serpent in thee be ſilent. As for thy laſt proof, 1 <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 13. What was this Word of Truth, if not Jeſus the Word of God, the ſure Word of Propheſie which ſhined in their dark hearts,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19. 1 Coll. 26.</note> which they knew not: Was not this the Myſtery unto them and all the blinde Gentiles: And was not this, through their Faith therein, the Goſpel of their Salvation: Were they not ſealed by that Holy Spirit of Promiſe, by beleeving in this VVord of Truth within them, which cannot be corrupted nor removed into a corner. Anſwer thoſe <hi>quaeries, Ionathan,</hi> without any jugling, or elſe let the mouth of the lyar be ſtopt, for ever mentioning the Name of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now to the ſecond Poſition, Thou breaths forth ſuch Fume as comes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115205:5"/>from the bottomleſs Pit, and ſayes I reckon thee among Drunkards, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſay, <hi>the Drunkards make their boaſt in this belief:</hi> If there be falſhood in my words,<note place="margin">Was not the Devil in <hi>Peter</hi> when Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Get thee behinde me Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant</hi>
               </note> why does not the Serpents wiſdom ſeek to confute them; but the words are true, and ſo the Devil's dumb as to ſuch a work; for the righteous Seed of God ariſes in thee, judging and condemning thee to be drunk with pride, paſſion, lying, wrath, and falſe accuſing, and that makes the Devil in thee rage, he would not be diſquieted; but the man of ſin muſt be tormented.</p>
            <p>Read thy figure in the <hi>Phariſee;</hi> 'tis ſeen by the Light who it is that hath two horns like a Lamb, yet ſpeaks like a Dragon, caſting forth floods of Indignation, and Serpentine Accuſations upon the ſimple. Turn to the Light of God within thee, and that true Prophet, <hi>Nathan</hi>-like, will tell thee,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art the man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ah! Shames thou not with thy falſe tongue, to tell me I contemn the Faith in the ſufferings of Chriſt, and thus arrogantly to ask me, <hi>How dare I thus contemptuouſly ſpeak of my Redeemer.</hi> (Thou canſt not call him thy Redeemer, till the Serpents head be broken in thee, and the lying Devil caſt out of thee) becauſe in my Paper I writ to this effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou, and they who feed your ſelves with the meerfrothy verball Faith in the ſufferings of the Man Chriſt Ieſus at Ieruſalem, and yet wallow in your wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, are not ſaved or redeemed from your ſins.</hi> Judge, O ye honeſt heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Nation, whether this language be a ſpeaking contemptuouſly of my Redeemer, yea or nay: Are they who wallow in their wickedneſs redeemed from ſin, by ſaying they beleeve in the ſufferings of Chriſt at Jeruſalem: Then what's the difference between a Saint and a Sinner: Then what need is there of purifying the heart. But the children of the Lord know none are redeemed from ſin, but ſuch as do forſake ſin, who ceaſe from doing evill, and turn from the evill of their wayes: Is the proud one redeemed from pride while he continues in that ſin; Is he not a ſervant of ſin that liveth in ſin: Is the cholerick haſty nature ſubdued, and that man redeemed from paſſion, while the paſsionate Devill hath dominion over him: the Lamb of God is meek and lowly, and ſo are all his tender Lambs. Now judge, O ye wiſe in heart, if the Scriptures call not him who ſuffered at Jeruſalem, the Man Chriſt Jeſus, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. May I not uſe the Language of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in that place; is it any ſin for me to call him by that Name which he gave himſelf; Read <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.40. <hi>But now ye ſeek to kill me, a</hi> Man <hi>that hath told you the truth:</hi> Yet I did call him the Man Chriſt Jeſus. Peruſe my Paper once again, <hi>Ionathan;</hi> ſee if I ſaid not, <hi>No other Ieſus do I own, but that Lamb of God which was ſlain from the beginning of the world;</hi> Did I not ſay, that I did own and reverence the Spirit of the living God in him,<note place="margin">Col. 29. Pſal. 45.7.</note> and <hi>that the ſulneſs of the God-head dwelt bodily in him; He was anointed above his fellows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ceaſe then thou ſlanderer from thy ſcandalous Accuſations, for my Redeemer I do reverence. Thou tells me in two ſeverall places, that I
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115205:5"/>crucifie Chriſt again; and yet breaks forth into rage becauſe I tell thee,<note place="margin">Ye have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and kill'd the Juſt &amp; he doth not reſiſt you, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>He is ſlain in thee;</hi> and asks me, <hi>if the Lamb that was ſlain be not alive for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore.</hi> In thee he is ſlain, in his Saints he is alive; but the Heavens which contain him is a Myſtery to thy dark minde: So let the Sot be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent.</p>
            <p>I need none of the lyars counſel, the falſe Prophets prating is not worth liſtning to; the bold Blaſphemer ſhall be met with for his Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: Thou bids me leave thoſe falſe Luminaries, and turn my feet into the Teſtimonies of the true Light. Wouldſt thou have me renounce my Redeemer; is this the reverence thou wouldſt have me to do him, to call him a falſe Luminary, becauſe the blaſphemer terms him ſo: The Lord rebuke thee, for the delight of my ſoul is in the Light of the world, Chriſt Jeſus; wouldſt thou have me now that I am waſhed to return again to my wallowing in the myre: When thou writes again, if that be thy meaning, ſay ſo man.</p>
            <p>The Leopard cannot change his ſpots, and 'tis hard for thee to leave thy lying: Thou ſayes I kill the Scriptures;<note place="margin">Yet the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures I own, for they are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable.</note> can that which is dead be killed; Doſt not thou in two ſeverall places call the Scriptures a dead Letter; and ſtill runs on in thy lying, ſaying, I am forced to run for ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to thoſe I account my enemies, who knows, thou ſayes, no other buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all with Chriſt, but buriall in water, calling them the chief Princes of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhech</hi> and <hi>Tuball.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the men thou means (<hi>viz.</hi> thoſe called Dippers) they are of age, let them anſwer for themſelves; if they be not enemies to the Croſs of Jeſus Chriſt, I ſhall not count them enemies to me; but how canſt thou prove that I run to them for ſhelter; is it becauſe I ſpeak of thy ſprinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; I never made any of them my Oracle therein. Thou ſayes, <hi>I bid thee prove whether Chriſt commanded baptiſm to his Diſciples, yea or nay; and did the Lord require it of his people to this day:</hi> What an abominable lye, beſides Non-ſence, haſt thou vented in two lines: My words are theſe, <hi>Is thy sprint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with water the baptiſm of Chriſt Ieſus, yea or nay; Did the Lord command that to his Diſciples, yea or nay; And does the Lord require it of his people to this day.</hi> I did never read nor know of one that pretends to more Piety then thou does, that ever excell'd or equall'd thee in thy devilliſh art of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; a notable Servant thou art to thy Maſter, and ſure thou art to receive thy Wages: <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. For the ſimples ſake I ſhall peruſe thoſe Scriptures thy Father ſends thee with to fight for his Kingdom, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38.41, 42. but I finde not ſprinckling with water there, nor ſo much as the word water: Nor does <hi>Acts</hi> 22.16. make for thy purpoſe, where 'tis ſaid, <hi>Ariſe and be baptized and waſh away thy ſins, calling on the Name of the Lord:</hi> Is ſprinckling with water once mentioned in this place; Or did <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> bid him be baptized with outward Water; Or could outward Water waſh away <hi>Sauls</hi> ſins: Anſwer thoſe quaeries without a lye, if thou canſt. As for <hi>Acts</hi> 10.47, 48, is it not clear, the Holy Ghoſt was received with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115205:6"/>outward Water; then where's the neceſſity of ſprinckling or dipping? Does not thy next, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.36, 37. intimate that it is but a thing indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, <hi>if thou beleeveſt,</hi> ſaith Philip, <hi>thou mayeſt;</hi> as much as if he had ſaid <hi>if thou beleeves outward water to be neceſſary to ſalvation, thou mayeſt be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized;</hi> did he not rather chooſe to cheriſh then deſtroy the weak faith of the Eunuch The laſt Proof thou claps in is no better then the reſt, <hi>They were all baptized, both men and women,</hi> but Water is wanting. Therefore ceaſe vain Jangler, for without adding to the Letter, theſe places are not for thy purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> was a Prophet, therefore his Miniſtration muſt end in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who is the fulfilling of the Law and the Prophets: Some of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles uſed circumciſion in the fleſh, had they a command from Chriſt for ſo doing; or was it not upon permiſſion? why doſt thou not as well plead for, and practiſe the one as the other? is not their authority of an equall purity, both by permiſſion, not by precept?</p>
            <p>In thy Reply to the 7th. <hi>Poſition,</hi> I finde thee ſo puzled, touchig Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that thou gives me no Anſwer to what I ſent thee, but would ſhuffle me off, bringing <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.2. But does he plead againſt Perfection as thou doſt? does he not ſay in the ſame verſe, <hi>if any man offend not in words, the ſame is a perfect man;</hi> the Scriptures were never writ that the Devill by them ſhould plead for ſin. Thou brings in <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. where <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, <hi>I know that in me (that is in my fleſh) dwells no good thing;</hi> From hence thou would infer, that in <hi>Paul</hi> there dwelt nothing that was good: But wilt thou ſay the Holy Ghoſt is not good? was not <hi>Paul</hi> filled with the Holy Ghoſt? if it were as thou would infer, then away with <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, and by conſequence with the reſt of the Scriptures, for they were all writ from one Spirit. If there was nothing good in <hi>Paul,</hi> then <hi>Paul</hi> muſt needs be a Seducer of the people: <hi>VVhen we were in the fleſh,</hi> ſayes Paul <hi>(in the unregenerate condition) the motions of ſin did work in our members, to bring forth fruit unto death; but now we are delivered from the Law, that we ſhould ſerve in newneſs of Spirit, not in the oldneſs of the Letter:</hi> And Rom. 8.8, 9. <hi>They that are in the Fleſh cannot pleaſe God, but ye are not in the Fleſh,</hi> (yet they were alive upon earth) <hi>but in the Spirit.</hi> That of <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. is to thee a myſtery, therefore Babler be ſilent, the Tree thou feeds on is accurſed. Thy piece of Lodgick ſhews what a <hi>Pagan</hi> thou art, <hi>That which is ſubject to mortality, loſs, and change, and miſtakes, is not perfect,</hi> thou ſayes, <hi>But mans humane ſtate in it ſelf is ſubject, &amp;c. therefore mans humane ſtate is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where doſt thou read this language of mans humane ſtate in all the Scripture? Conſider of this in the cool of the day; that which is born of the Fleſh is Fleſh; but that which is born of the Spirit is Spirit, is that ſubject to mortality loſs and change: that which is born not of blood, nor of the will of man, but of God, that doth not commit ſin, that cannot ſin, becauſe 'tis born of God, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.9.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115205:6"/>
            <p>Now becauſe thou art ſo ſilent to what I ſent thee concerning Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I here return thee ſome few things which my Letter mentions, as to that; <hi>Muſt the devill have power over thee while thou lives, to make thee his veſſel to do his will and work here on earth, and doſt thou hope to have Heaven for thy wages when thou dyes? Knows thou not, as the tree falls ſo it lyes, and the wages of ſin is death? And is not the tabernacle of God with men,</hi> Rev. 21. <hi>Does not the Lord ſay,</hi> I <hi>wil dwel in them and walk in them, &amp;c. is not this done upon earth? Does not the Lord delight to ſave his people from their ſins? Does he juſtifie and not ſanctifie his people? does he forgive ſins and not give power over ſins? what is the end of the Lords being preſent with his people and in his people, but ſheild them from ſin and Satan, and to keep them pure without spot or wrinckle, who are willing to be guided by him?</hi> And when thou writes again, either confeſs, or deny the Truth, in thy Anſwer to thoſe Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <p>But why doſt thou deny that to be the true Spirit, or that to be true Unction which is not received by the Letter? had not <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the reſt of the holy men of God (who lived before <hi>Moſes</hi> writ the Letter) had not they, I ſay, the Spirit of Truth within them? were there not many deceitfull Serpents, filthy ſpirits, like thine, in their dayes? and had they any outward writing given them as an infallible Rule to diſcover falſe ſpirits with? was not the ſpirit of God in them the infallible Rule, and ſole Touch-ſtone for the tryall of ſpirits, which were true, which were falſe? Did <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles receive the Spirit of Truth by vertue of hearing, or reading any writings or books without them?</p>
            <p>That which I brought out of 1 John 2. as to the Annointing ſtands unſhaken, and cannot be removed by all the Brats of Babylon; does not <hi>John</hi> admoniſh them to keep to the Unction within which they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? does he bid them make his Epiſtle their Rule to walk by; or could they have been ſeduced if they had kept to the Annointing within, though <hi>Johns</hi> Epiſtle had not been ſent to them? Anſwer thoſe quaeries: Yet do I not deny but the Saints in their infancie are capable of good counſel, and may admit of a leading by the hand, &amp; let him that is confirmed ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en his Brethren. Thy carping at the ſpirits interpretation of 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. ſhews the blindneſs of the <hi>Babylonian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He who can make a good Confeſſion, and give a good account of Chriſt Jeſus in his own fleſhly Tabernacle, he is of God; this Expoſition cannot by the Serpents ſubtilty be ſhaken; as for the Pope, both him and thee I do deny, abominable lyars are you both; he is thy brother, though thou bawls againſt him, you are both ſervants to one Maſter, the man of ſin; he denies Chriſt come in the fleſh of his Saints, and ſo doſt thou; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Antichriſts you both be; it's but the lyar that tels me my Maſter hath not commanded me to judge; he whom thou boaſts came not to judg the world, but to ſave the world, ſayes in the next words, He that rejecteth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115205:7"/>me and receiveth not my word, hath one that judgeth him, and ſo haſt thou, for thou rejecteſt him, he is my witneſs, and he came not to bring Peace,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.2.</note> but a Sword to the man of ſin whom thou ſerveſt.</p>
            <p>But if the Saints ſhall not judge the world, thou muſt make <hi>Paul</hi> a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar like thy ſelf, And does <hi>not the Spiritual man judge all things, and he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is judged of no man:</hi> But ſince thou art ſo much againſt judgement, tell me by what authority doſt thou judge me for an Enemy of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with a deal of ſuch like Antichriſtian Rubbiſh, which reaches me not; why doſt thou judge thoſe people called <hi>Dippers,</hi> calling them the chief Princes of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhech</hi> and <hi>Tuball,</hi> ſaying, <hi>they know no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> buriall of Chriſt, but buriall in water:</hi> And by what Authority doſt thou judge the Prieſts of the Nation for Antichriſtians. Anſwer thoſe quaeries when thou writes again.</p>
            <p>In one of thy Arguments thou ſhames not to affirm, <hi>that the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of the words of Chriſt, is Spirit and life in it ſelf:</hi> and in another of the ſame mettal, (for they both come from one Mint, and have both but one Father) thou concludes, the Spirit of God in the Apoſtles, who were Saints, is the Rule to try, and diſcovery of falſe ſpirits and then falls to thy old vain of boaſting, that this Argument I cannot deny in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part; but indeed the man is ſo accuſtomed to lye, that 'tis a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for him to ſpeak true: Say, <hi>Ionathan,</hi> when did I deny that the spirit of God in the Apoſtles while they lived upon earth, was their Rule for them to try and diſcover falſe ſpirits, does not my Letter ſpeak the ſame Language; but did not the ſpirit of God in them at their death return to God that gave it them; wouldſt thou have me be as ſottith as thy ſelf, to ſay and unſay, and own their writings to be the ſpirit of God: but I have little pleaſure to take thus in thy Dung-hill, only 'tis my deſire the weak may not be wooryed by, but beware of ſuch Foxes and Wolves in ſheeps clothing. Thou charges me for a lyar, for ſaying thou owns the Letter to be the Rule; but one thing is, I need not go far to fetch my proof, thou haſt given it under thy own hand in theſe words,<note place="margin">See thy Reply to the 12th. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore the Scriptures are the ſure and infallible Rule to try the Spirits whether they be of God or no;</hi> yet for all this, and thy other argument, wherein thou calls them ſpirit and life in it ſelf, (under the name of the Words of Chriſt) thou calls them twice in this following argument of thine, the dead Letter; <hi>He that deſires to be tryed by the true Touch-ſtone, the infallible Rule, the living Principle of God, the Light of Chriſt in the Saints conſciences, the Spirit of truth, and would not be tryed by the dead Letter, his spirit is of God, he's guided by the spirit of Promiſe,</hi> but <hi>Jonathan Johnſon</hi> deſires to be tryed as aboveſaid, not by the dead Letter, therefore his ſpirit is of God, he's guided by the Spirit of Promiſe. Thus thy charge is ſoon taken of, and the lyar found lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in thy own boſom; how hath the Heathen raged, and caſt forth his Floods of indignation againſt me, for calling the Declaration a dead Letter, and yet ſpeaks the ſame ſeveral times in this argument: Didſt thou
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115205:7"/>not cry up the letter to be the in-let to the ſpirit of promiſe, &amp; bid me leave my falſe luminary, &amp; yet here owns the light of Chriſt in the conſcience to be the ſpirit of truth, ſurely the man thought he might ſay &amp; unſay as he liſt, and took me to be as very a for as himſelf, or elſe hath a very weak me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and that's very bad for ſo great a lyar as he is: I did never read groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer contradictions to my knowledge, then have dropt from the pen of this painted Pagan: And yet for all this folly &amp; confuſion, he muſt needs give me another rotten reed of AEgypt, as it were for a farewel, in an argument, the ſubſtance whereo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is thus: <hi>They who were Maſter-builders,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>muſt needs be the true Touch-stone; but the Apostles were Master-builders,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>whom</hi> M. M. <hi>denies to be tryed by, calling their preaching and teachings dead and lifeleſs, therefore his spirit is the spirit of error.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a forgetful, or wilful lying Beaſt is this; did he not but even now a little before in his other Argument, ſay, that he himſelf deſired to be tried by the light in the Saints conſciences, and not by the dead letter, and ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> taxes me with the ſpirit of error for the ſame thing: O bluſh, and be aſhamed! But for further anſwer. According to the grace of God which is given unto me as a wiſe <hi>Maſter-builder, I have laid the foundation,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10.<note place="margin">Col. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> He built upon the rock: <hi>Other foundation then that is laid can no man lay, which is Ieſus Chriſt in all, Iew and Greek, Barbarian, Scithian, bond and free.</hi> To this unction within did the Apoſtles direct the people, and if there had not been a royal ſeed of God left in eveey man and woman, to have anſwered, owned and received the teſtimony of the Apoſtles, they might have wandred all the world over, and have ſpent all their life-time, and not have gained one convert, but there was a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for God in all, and that which lay dead, did at the hearing of the voice of the Son of God live, and the Apoſtle was ſent to open the blind eye of thoſe Gentiles, who had eyes to ſee, yet ſaw not the Lamb of God the Lord of Glory crucified in them; ſo that great myſtery of Chriſt in them the hope of glory, was then to them revealed and made manifeſt; ſo here, that which was the foundation that was the Touch-ſtone, and Chriſt in all, the Unction, the Annoynting within was the Foundation of the Apoſtles, that which they built upon; therefore the unction, the annoynting within, the light in all conſciences, that's the true Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, and the infallible rule for the tryal of ſpirits which be true, which be falſe. Thus I have traced the Serpent in moſt of his crooked holes and windings, even almoſt unto wearineſs; that which follows is to you, poor hearts, who are ſo wedded to your water, that you count no man a Saint who ſubmits not to your ceremony. Anſwer me in good earneſt, Can your <hi>Diana</hi> ſatisfie a hungry ſoul? are you not feeding upon that which is not the bread from heaven? Is it your building the Tombs, or garniſhing the Sepulchres of the righteous with painted expreſſions, and ſmooth gloſſes, that can make you paſs for pure Saints, now the bright morning ſtar is come to diſcover you? Is it the putting away the filth of the fleſh by waſhing the body in outward water; or the anſwer of a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115205:8"/>a good conſcience towards God, that is well pleaſing unto God? and who can witneſs the anſwer of a good conſcience towards God, that is not guided by the light of God in his conſcience? and are you guided by that of God in your conſciences, who are not to come to yea and nay, in your dealings? are you guided by the light of God, and yet dare not uſe the language of God and his Saints recorded in the Scriptures? are you guided by the light of God in your conſciences, who yet live in reſpect of perſons, and be conformable to the vain cuſtomes and faſhions of the heathen, and are not yet brought to the brideling of the tongue? Be not angry hereat; for deer is my love to that of God in you; Ah! how ſhould I rejoyce to ſee you joyn your ſelves to the children of the Lord! ah, ſeek no longer the living among the dead! contend no longer about that which brings no contentment to the ſoul! Would you ſee the King of Saints? Loe, hee's within you, go not forth: Ah! be no longer loyterers; <hi>Great is the harveſt, and the labourers but few; He that is not with me, is againſt me; Be no longer in the number of thoſe who forget God; Fight no longer for that which cannot ſtand before the Lord; you have too long idolized your ceremony, and therefore like the brazen Serpent is it broken in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Paul</hi> told the people, <hi>He had not ſhunned to declare unto them all the counſel of God,</hi> but where did he mention Water-Baptiſme as a branch thereof? if it had been of the counſel of God, certainly <hi>Paul</hi> durſt not have concealed it. Did he not fore-ſee that thing began to be idolized in his days? did not contentions then ariſe among the people, ſome ſaying, I <hi>am of Paul;</hi> another, I <hi>of Apollo;</hi> ſome of <hi>Cephas,</hi> ſome of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he knowing it not to be a precept, but a permiſſive practice, Iaid it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and thanked God that he had baptized none but <hi>Criſpus</hi> and <hi>Gaius,</hi> and the houſhold of <hi>Stephanas;</hi> an infallible ſign it was no better than a Ceremony,<note place="margin">1 <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 3.21.</note> had it been a command durſt he have diſcontinued it? nay, does he not plainly tell the people, <hi>he was not ſent to baptiſe, but to preach the Goſpel?</hi> and does not <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeak plain enough to the prudent? does he count Water-Baptiſin any better than a figure, pointing out the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance the anſwer of a good conſcience. Are figures and ſhadows to abide or flie away? Which of you (would you be but truly honeſt to the light of God in you) durſt poſitively affirm outward Water to be the Baptiſm of Chriſt? Is not his a Baptiſm of <hi>Sufferings?</hi> Be not afraid to <hi>take up the daily Croſs,</hi> but like <hi>valiant ſouldiers,</hi> enter the field, and <hi>deſpiſe the ſhame:</hi> Be not fearful of <hi>Giants</hi> in the way, for <hi>his yoke is eaſie, and his burden light.</hi> He that commands, gives power; be you but <hi>willing,</hi> and <hi>power</hi> will not be wanting to level thoſe <hi>hills and mountains of corruption within you.</hi> Do but ſet your <hi>hearts</hi> to love that <hi>Royal Seed of God,</hi> the <hi>light of Ieſus Chriſt</hi> in your <hi>conſciences,</hi> and that you ſhall witneſs to be <hi>power invincible,</hi> to reſiſt and quench the <hi>fiery darts of the Devill. O come away, and do no longer ſtay, left the door of mercy be ſhut againſt you.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Martin Maſon.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:115205:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115205:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115205:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
